A Guide to the George M. Parker Jr. World War II Papers, 1941-1945
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
George M. Parker Jr. World War II Papers, 1941-1945
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2008-022
4 containers; 1.7 cu. ft.
World War 2 letters of George Marinor Parker Jr., Army Air Force, of Water View, Virginia, his mother's wartime diary, and related ephemera and correspondence.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The George M. Parker Jr. World War II Papers were purchased by Special Collections in 2008.
Biographical Information
George Marinor Parker Jr. (17 August 1921-1 January 1999) was born to George and Angie Parker of Water View, Virginia. He had two sisters, Audrey and Frances ("Sis"). In March and April 1942, he was trained and then worked as a mechanic at Newport News. He enlisted in the army on 5 May 1942. He spent his first year and a half of service in the continental United States, going through training and then working at airfields in Texas, Oregon, and California. He was deployed and arrived in England on 2 November 1943. He served in France from August 1944 to 16 October 1944. He was transferred to Kassel, Germany on 16 May 1945, just over a month after Kassel was captured by the Allies. He left Kassel 21 October 1945 for France, where he stayed until his return to the States at the end of November. He was married some time after his return to the States, presumably to his friend Nellie, who, he told his sister in a letter from 1945, he was planning to marry despite apparent maternal disapproval. He settled down in Water View, Virginia, where he lived until his death.
Scope and Content
The George M. Parker Jr. World War II Papers consists primarily of letters written by George Marinor Parker Jr. of Water View, Virginia to his mother and sisters while he was away in the army. The bulk of the collection is from May 1942-November 1945. Additionally, there are a number of letters written by George Jr. between 1930, when he was in second grade, and 1935. There are also a number of letters addressed to his sister Aubrey from 1947, a 76 page manuscript diary that his mother kept throughout most of the war, and ephemera relating to his service. The letters focus primarily on events at home, the hens, the health of family, etc., although in many letters George describes parts of his daily routine, including detailed descriptions of meals the soldiers are given.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series:
I. Letters of George Parker Jr., 1942-1945. These letters, arranged chronologically, were written by George Jr. during his time in the Army Air Force. For most of his time in the service, he wrote either a letter or card to his mother every few days, and letters to his sister Frances and friend Ruth less frequently.
II. Cards and V-mail of George Parker Jr., 1941-1945. These cards and V-mail letters, arranged chronologically, were written by George Jr. starting with several cards sent during his employment at Newport News, and continued by cards and V-mail messages (when he was deployed overseas) from throughout his time in the service.
III. Miscellany and ephemera, 1930-1947. This series consists of letters and cards George Jr. wrote to his sisters while between the ages of 8 and 13 (1930-1935).
The series also contains a 76-page manuscript diary maintained by George Jr.'s mother during the war (1942-1945). The diary contains information about when she, her daughters, and his local friends heard from George Jr., as well as occasional glimpses into her own life, such as noting when one of her daughters visited, or when she had dinner with a friend.
In addition, the series contains a book of notes from his sister Audrey's studies in education (ca. 1946), a body of his sisters' correspondence (1947), and various ephemeral items relating to the Parker family and particularly his service in the Army (1942-1945, n.d.). The materials are organized chronologically.
Contents List
- Letters of George Parker Jr., 1942-1945
  - Letters
    - Dec 1941-17 Jun 1942 (Box-folder 1:1)
    - 22 Jun 1942-8 Aug 1942 (Box-folder 1:2)
    - 11 Aug 1942-22 Sep 1942 (Box-folder 1:3)
    - 27 Sep 1942-11 Nov 1942 (Box-folder 1:4)
    - 12 Nov 1942-19 Dec 1942 (Box-folder 1:5)
    - 22 Dec 1942-16 Jan 1943 (Box-folder 1:6)
    - 17 Jan 1943-13 Apr 1943 (Box-folder 1:7)
    - 16 Apr 1943-25 Jul 1943 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - 27 Jul 1943-10 Nov 1943 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - 11 Nov 1943-14 Aug 1944 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - 29 Aug 1944-27 Jun 1945 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - 1 Jul 1945-14 Oct 1945 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - 16 Sep 1945 [i.e. 16 Oct 1945]-21 Nov 1945 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Cards and V-mail of George Parker Jr., 1941-1945
  - Cards and V-mail
    - 1941-24 Nov 1942 (Box-folder 3:1)
    - 28 Jan 1943-21 Mar 1944 (Box-folder 3:2)
    - 30 Mar 1944-29 Aug 1944 (Box-folder 3:3)
    - 4 Sep 1944-16 May 1945 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - 29 May 1945-7 Oct 1945 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Miscellany and ephemera, 1930-1947
  - Letters George wrote to his sisters as a child, 1 letter from his mother to his sister, and one letter addressed to his mother, 1930-1935 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Letters from other members of the military to George's mom; George's mother's diary, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Letters among other members of George's family, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Cards among other members of George's family, 16 Nov 1946-31 Mar 1947 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Cards among other members of George's family, 2 Apr 1947-11 Jun 1947, n.d. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, 1942-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 4:4)